Guide to the Collection of Bookplates from the British West Indies
Yale University Arts Library
Collection of Bookplates from the British West Indies
1741-1913
BKP 73
Yale University Arts Library
1.25
(3 boxes)
This is a collection of mostly 18th- and 19th-century armorial bookplates from territories formerly known as the British West Indies or from individuals who were associated with those territories. Most of the bookplates belonged to private individuals, although the collection does contain a few institutional bookplates from various library, university, or social organizations.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
The Yale Bookplate Collection was formerly housed in Sterling Memorial Library. The collection was incorporated into the Arts of the Book Collection in 1984 and then moved to the Seeley G. Mudd Library in 1990. In 2011 it was transferred to the Robert B. Haas Family Arts Library.
Associated Materials
See also the Pearson-Lowenhaupt Collection of English and American Bookplates (Call # BKP 30).
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Scope and Contents
This is a collection of mostly 18th- and 19th-century armorial bookplates from territories formerly known as the British West Indies or from individuals who were associated with those territories. Most of the bookplates belonged to private individuals, although the collection does contain a few institutional bookplates from various library, university, or social organizations.
Most of the bookplates are mounted on paper cards, measuring 5 x 8 inches. The mounts bear evidence of various inscriptions, including the place of origin (or association) and one or more numbers, some of which may correspond to the identification numbers used by the Franks Collection of Bookplates at the British Museum.
The following is a list of the territories identified in the collection: Antigua, Bahamas, Barbados, Bermuda, British Guiana, Dominica, Grenada, Jamaica, Martinique, Montserrat, Nevis, St. Croix, St. Kitts, St. Vincent, Tobago, Trinidad, and the Virgin Islands.
Arrangement
Organized into four series: I. Bookplates – Mounted. II. Bookplates – Unmounted. III. Scrapbook. IV. Ephemera.
Bookplates; Bookplates
- Bookplates – Mounted, Series I
  Arrangement
  Arranged in original alphabetical order.
  - Adair – Austen, 1878 undated; 26 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Baillie – Beete, 1784 undated; 20 (Box 1, Folder 2)
  - Belmore – Briggs, circa 1770 undated; 20 items (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Brisbane – Byndloss, circa 1770 1779 undated; 26 (Box 1, Folder 4)
  - Cameron – Codrington, circa 1760 undated; 24 items (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Colebrooke – Cussans, undated; 28 items (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Dallas – Dehaney, undated; 21 items (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Desbrisay – Dyer, circa 1800 undated; 15 items (Box 1, Folder 8)
  - Earl – Estridge, circa 1790 undated; 12 items (Box 1, Folder 9)
  - Fairholme – Furlong, 1741 circa 1790 undated; 28 (Box 1, Folder 10)
  - Gale – Gomm, undated; 20 items (Box 1, Folder 11)
  - Gordon – Guiana, Bishops College, circa 1770 undated; 17 items (Box 1, Folder 12)
    Scope and Contents
    This folder contains an institutional bookplate for Bishops College in British Guiana.
  - Haggatt – Henslowe, 1796 undated; 26 (Box 1, Folder 13)
  - Hering – Hyde, circa 1750-1820 undated; 26 items (Box 1, Folder 14)
  - Ingram – Julius, circa 1790 1805 undated; 16 (Box 2, Folder 15)
  - Keane – Lawrence, undated; 22 items (Box 2, Folder 16)
  - Leighton – Livius, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 17)
    This folder contains an institutional bookplate for the Literary Society in Barbados.
  - Long – Lyons, 1790 undated; 26 (Box 2, Folder 18)
  - Macartney – Marryat, circa 1791 undated; 21 items (Box 2, Folder 19)
  - Martin – Maynard, 1815-1830 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 20)
  - Melvill – Musgrave, 1903 undated; 26 (Box 2, Folder 21)
  - Neate – Oughton, 1806-1849 1913 undated; 27 (Box 2, Folder 22)
  - Paris – Pedder, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 23)
    This folder contains an exchange letter, dated April 27, 1883, which is attached to the Parsons bookplate. The letter is written by Daniel Parsons of Stuarts Lodge, Malvern Wells, Worcestershire, England, and is addressed to [J. W. Lloyd, Esq.?].
  - Pemberton – Prevost, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 24)
  - Rebello – Rutherford, undated; 24 items (Box 2, Folder 25)
  - Sage – Smyth, undated; 20 items (Box 2, Folder 26)
  - Snagg – Symes, undated; 15 items (Box 2, Folder 27)
  - Taylor – Union Hall Library (Jamaica), 1797 1870 undated; 21 (Box 2, Folder 28)
    This folder contains an institutional bookplate for the Union Hall Library in Jamaica.
  - Vassall – Waterman, 1807 undated; 20 (Box 3, Folder 29)
    This folder contains a bookplate and proof for Spencer L. H. Vassall.
  - Webb – Wilson, undated; 22 items (Box 3, Folder 30)
  - Woodbridge – Young, undated; 15 items (Box 3, Folder 31)
- Bookplates – Unmounted, Series II
  - East – Hunter, undated; 4 (Box 3, Folder 32)
- Scrapbook, Series III
  - Scrapbook, 1902; 1 (Box 3, Folder 33)
    This folder contains a half-leather bound scrapbook with the title West Indian Ex-Libris and the date 1902 stamped on the spine. The bookplates have been removed, although some inscriptions similar to those found on the mounts of bookplates (see Series I) remain on the scrapbook pages.
- Ephemera, Series IV
  - Blank bookplate mount, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 34)
  - Memo, undated; 1 (Box 3, Folder 35)
    This folder contains a handwritten memo about this collection from Warren Hiram Lowenhaupt, former Curator of Bookplates.